this computer okay thank you Joe for
making time for this conversation we
briefly met during the regenerative
practitioner training that I took and
helped to organize here in Europe in
2017 and can't believe it's already been
more than two years since we last talked
so you know there must be big now she's
in Hartford
so yeah wonderful to speak with you and
I looked at your bio today and what
stood out was that you've been a builder
farmer a teacher a naturalist a writer a
storyteller and a permaculturist for 30
years and in this series that I've
started of having conversations with who
I consider elders of joy regenerative
practice people like you and I I like to
start with MIT to just talk about what
got them onto this path what like maybe
some of the key moments that really you
still think of that he made a decision
there or yeah what has informed your
path and and tell us a little bit about
how you got here now yeah great that's a
great question and as you know right the
way we understand things is through
stories there's a way in which wherever
you are and the story you're connected
to everything else in that story both
behind us and in front of us and for me
it's really clear I grew up my dad was a
builder so I spent a lot of time in that
industry which is one of the last places
where people work outside except for
agriculture right and at that time there
were no nail guns there were power tools
obviously but it was very much still a
craftsperson
skill oriented trade of oriented
endeavor and I was born in the city in
Philadelphia and when I was about eight
we moved out to the country where my mom
had grown up what was then the far edge
of the
burbs has now been swallowed by the
suburbs of Philadelphia and so I grew up
in fields and farms and barns and spent
most of my time in the forest remnant
forest behind my parents house and I
didn't know the names of species I
didn't know many of those things but it
spoke to me
and it was where I felt comfortable and
things made sense and so that's informed
my life ever since that there's ways in
which much of my life has been a way of
trying to give back to everything that I
was given by that beautiful little
forest and spending so much time in that
forest I began to wonder about the
original people there and they how they
had lived in that place in different
ways and so I began to read all the
books I could and came upon a copy of
Black Elk speaks in the mall one weekend
with my dad and it to my world that it
was being a child of about the same age
he was when he had his great vision it
didn't it wasn't well filtered and so it
gave me an entirely different view of
the world of not only this sacred
spiritual level of reality and of the
living world but people being a part of
a harmonious living whole and moving
around and being in relation to all the
cycles and changes and developments and
evolutions and contributing to those in
the landscape and that more than human
community right everyone as elders so I
was whatever 10 12 years old stealing my
mom's Virginia Slims to make tobacco
offerings to trees before I cut them
down to build forts right entirely
clueless took ideas like cultural
appropriation or anything else because I
was I was just trying to follow what
spoke to me and so I when I went to
college and I came here to New Mexico I
had a
job um remodeling a house because that's
what I knew how to do I had grown up
doing that and we were almost done and a
landscaper came and started to repair
the damage we had wrought to the land
replanting native grasses and native
plants and it made me realize I would
much rather do that and create the
damage so I got a job doing native
landscaping here in Santa Fe and I did
that throughout college with plants to
the southwest and then I became involved
with the agricultural seed saving
project here at one of the pueblos gaya
wingait San Juan Pablo and we put
together this amazing seed bank that
went on to become seeds of change and I
began to learn about permaculture my
boss at plants the Southwest was
actually been Haggard and that's where I
first saw permaculture and permaculture
too and I went off and did a
permaculture course at new alchemy under
the late 80s with John Todd and Bill
McClarty and Roslyn Crissy and all these
heavy hitters and my second PhD
supervisor so I know right yeah hugely
influential on me and soon after that I
there was a weekend workshop here in
Lamy New Mexico with Bill Mollison and I
realized I had gotten a huge amount of
rice crispies and not a whole lot of the
treat so there was a lot of very great
depth into techniques and technologies
and not so much about their relationship
or reading landscape or any of that so I
did a two-week design course with
Mollison in 88 89 drylands course and
then went on to begin to teach and
practice all of these things I was
married to a woman from Santa Clara
Pueblo at the time couple of Wayne gay
and we developed flowering tree
permaculture and so we looked at what
people had done here forever and looked
at other species that could be brought
in and talked to old men and looked at
the landscape and went to old ruins and
that site as a way of seeing do these
things work and how do they work here
with these people and I did a video
about this a couple of years ago called
greening the desert 30 years greening
the desert you could see it a flowering
tree I'm sorry at pattern mind org and
the beginning sequence of that film is
zooming in on Google Earth and you see
the desert Southwest and as you get in
you start to see this little postage
stamp green food forest Oasis and when I
first made that sequence I patted myself
on the back and thought how wonderful
that was and in the middle of the night
I woke up and realized my point was not
just to demonstrate these things worked
it was to change how we see the land and
how we relate if I had done it
effectively that little Oasis would have
spread everywhere it would be like the
first blades of grass in a meadow
instead of that it remained this little
isolated postage stamp and his in guy's
garden and people from around the world
I've seen it and been inspired by it but
I was not intelligent enough at the time
to know how to design a process to
engage the community to change how we
saw the land and treated the land
differently I had this mentality of
build it they will come to show that you
could do this and everybody's gonna
change their mind and change their lives
and that was very nice such a deep
lesson I mean of course we need these
watering holes and we need these
examples but how much energy of amazing
people is going into making their one
permaculture demonstration being
stewards of those two six fifteen acres
and doing a beautiful job with it but
but not looking at how the yogurt
culture can turn the milk into yogurt
absolutely yes that it's not
strategically placed
it's simply placed and it's also think
we're materialists is what it made me
realize that I thought I could change
this physical thing and then that will
change people's minds instead of
realizing that no actually the strategic
place to work is in our minds in our
consciousness and one of the things I do
is tracking which we'll talk a bit more
about but when we see everything we see
is a track right but we think it's
reality but it's a track of a biological
reality it's a physical track of a
biological reality and my body your body
the cup the building's the books the
food forests and then it's I was
thinking the other day it's almost as if
we think that oh there's a track of a
deer if I take a stick and I turn those
deer tracks into elk tracks it doesn't
make the deer and into an elk right that
the the underlying pattern that left the
track must be changed to change the
tracks it doesn't go backwards right and
so back in the day Ben Haggard and Tim
Murphy and myself doing permaculture
work and teaching permaculture began to
notice that our projects were not having
the effects we were after that they
didn't have a long life they certainly
were not permanent in any way they got
second-guessed all of those kinds of
things so we encountered bobandpam
Lemang ben and tim ton of course they
took and they realized that we were
looking at same things they were looking
at from an organizational development
point of view and systems thinking point
of view from a more grounded
experiential point of view so we also
were very aware of the need for how we
saw the world to change and systems
thinking so we formed Regenesis this 109
TS so over 20 years ago this is just
very briefly this is fascinating to me
because in many lee years later
there was this little German guy and
doing his his master's at Omaha college
and kind of getting on a path around
2001 and and I ended up doing this PhD
in 2006 where just what you trained
friends slightly differently but exactly
the same things of this issue that
everything is an intervention that era
did that designs go on designing and
that we live in a world that is full of
the patterns of previous design
decisions that we remain questioning and
that inform us this loop between
worldview and design and and they're
like like Churchill said first we shape
our buildings and then our buildings
shape us like really taking that
awareness to everything we do and how it
leaves that track and and then shapes
reality space and so the I I then called
the work upstream from that meta design
that that shifts the worldview and value
system in the underlying thinking
patterns that the the organizing ideas
that then make people bring forth a
different world so that's why I think my
iced tea so deeply resonate with the
work of Regenesis because I've sort of
dabbled in trying to understand the same
thing and and and kind of given it
initially an academic framework in the
last 10 years 15 years also tried to
apply that somehow in my work and yeah
just just in parentheses for us yeah
great article Genesis and now 30 years
ago 20-some years ago maybe 25 years ago
now and one of the big
Schiff's we made was as you're saying
going as far upstream as we could and we
decided to focus on the real estate
development field because it is the most
destructive in agriculture some of the
most destructive forces on the face of
the planet and has this word development
in it and it's very much a
misunderstanding of how do you develop
the value of land of developing the
value of places help that be revealed
and so that's what we focused on these
20-some years and he you know took some
things from John miles and writing about
a regenerative development back in what
the 70s 80s and tried to one of the
things that really got us all to see is
that permaculture design is not about
designing a site it's not about physical
design of where things go in
relationship to one another that is a
level that we all enter at but it is
re-examining and designing as you're
saying the design process and because we
don't we we designed both things and the
processes to put them into being and
it's often those processes that are the
have the greatest effects in the world
but most of them are habitual whether
it's how we go about building a building
or making dinner or getting from here to
there and so we've worked for these
20-some years to get the development
industry to begin to one appreciate
place and how places behave all uniquely
and differently just like each of us and
every snowflake and that's where their
potential lies and to begin to
re-examine our worldview and to actually
engage stakeholders as an essential
piece of it not to convince them to let
you do what you want to do or to get
everybody's opinion but to go on
mental journey together to reimagine
what this place could be understand this
place is a very deep level as a larger
being that we are like organs within and
to look for how do we help regenerate
the innate potential in each of us in
this place as a socio-ecological hole so
it's neither just a piece of dirt on the
map it's a living system of which we are
an essential piece and have essential
roles that living systems are dying for
us to play and all all the boundaries in
that transforming whole and somewhat
real and arbitrary at the same time like
wait a they are all fluid and and and
also wholeness is not auditory so so
it's not that you're just a piece in
that larger hole you are actually it mmm
it's like this is one thing that I
learned from from Henry port often
Gertie and science that and this real
what Henry calls authentic wholeness
that has very strongly actually also
informed the work of um David Seaman and
and Christopher Alexander that holes are
not additive they like authentic holds
the parts in the hole
bring forth each other in a in a dynamic
relationship and well I often tell this
story of when my oldest son was I don't
know four months old I was holding him
at night and he was sleeping excuse me
and having built things my whole life I
thought about how I would make his
miraculous body and so I would of course
frame him up I'd put all those bones
together and attach it with tendons and
ligaments and muscles and I'd run his
circulatory system and his nervous
system and install all of his organs and
she them with skin and make sure all the
joints worked fill him up with blood and
some food and some water and start him
up and it made me
realize that that is how I and I think
we think about designing and making
anything even a curriculum or a school
or a business that we think we are going
to create it structurally and then
articulate it somehow and then we turn
it on and it begins to operate this is
such a fascinating like the metaphor you
of the because I've just gone through
this with my and two and a half year old
daughter and coming back coming from a
biological training and and a long line
of medics man my mom and my grandfather
and so on I
Lucia just seem like even from the
beginning that we know that we were
pregnant and the thought that there was
this magic process happening of two
cells meeting and then going to four and
to 8 into 16 and then this little ball
and then suddenly it was going through
all the evolutionary stages of kind of
looking like fish looking like chicken
looking like and and and they months
later this magical being is come into
the world and and since then it's just
been evolving like you see as involved
so rapidly and every day I thought I
can't believe we really think that our
technology has all technology has
anything against the intelligence and
the complexity of biological processes
the arrogance we have to even compare
what we can do crudely within that tech
technological mechanistic frame and how
how nature works with processes it's one
of the reasons I've come to call biology
metaphysics because it may be in
physical bodies of all sorts but the
life is is not physically within
anything right it's it's the exchanges
that are happening right as soon as I
stop breathing in the atmosphere stops
rushing into my lungs and every cell and
rushing back out and and my heart stops
beating and I stop water and food stop
jumping up off the earth and through my
mouth and that
the life is the exchange within those
physical mechanical structures and
there's this a couple remarkable things
in there your daughter my son each of us
was never not a hole right and right the
river was never not a hole and all of us
the tree and each of us was made our
structure was made by carrying out the
processes that were still carrying out
metabolizing nutrients with the use of
oxygen moving learning the water flowing
made the river right the tree taking
atmospheric carbon and sunlight and
putting into the earth and taking water
nutrients and putting them up into the
sky that started when that seed was
sprouting right and so all biological
structures were formed carrying out the
processes they were formed to carry out
it's a remarkable shift in how we view
the world and that's what I'm always
looking for to to things and we're going
a little bit on detour here but this is
fascinating for me and because I wanted
to get there later and it's almost like
I can encapsulate it with with
suppose like like said 250 years ago who
doesn't see nature everywhere sees her
know we're in the right light mm-hmm and
when when even like I even as I was
speaking earlier about technology and
life I I was observing myself and
thinking well yeah but here you are
again creating a dualism between
technology and nature and and the best
way I've come to if you really sit
deeply with that sentence of good and
and it kind of makes sense that the
earth within
the solar system within the cosmos all
of that is nested wholeness and even if
you stay just within the biosphere it's
one transforming process of which
nothing is outside therefore all our
technology has to somehow also be seen
as nature and that jars with me to some
extent the only way I can reintegrate
that is to say they are adaptive and
maladaptive pathways in the evolutionary
journey and those kind of like atomic
power plant or a nuclear weapon um I
just maladaptive dead ends and that
natural system by I'm just how do you
how do you square that nature everywhere
and then our deep attention to learning
as nature from nature to then be able to
design as nature and and bring health
and wholeness to the system that we
participate in but then also like that
brings us forth and that we co-create
this because there's this dimension of
mind as well like life because you said
life is it not easier to say that
everything is a life extent so it's one
of the reasons why we always talk about
living systems as opposed to nature
right and it all of this also carries
over into what we call mind if you
listen to a Buddhist they will say your
mind
right it's not some intellectual thing
that's separate and it's what's behind
Gregory Bateson's mind and nature and
necessary unity right so if we so if we
go this route that everything is a
living system including a business
including a factory right as long as
there is what we could would consider a
living system so if if a system is
something that is organized around a
purpose right then a bicycle has a
purpose
but a pile of bicycle parts does not
it's not organized around assists a
purpose and once I get onto that bicycle
and I'm a part of that living system I'm
operating it in that direction yeah and
so one of the profound let me tell a
story and then I'll go here so I have
had the honor and privilege for over 20
years to help teach a Native American
permaculture design course here in New
Mexico and we've had people from all
over the hemisphere North and South and
one year early on we were up at the
Greece Pueblo and it was a bunch of
students some of them were high school
students from the Greece and you
probably know great all of the issues of
incarceration and poverty and abuse and
alcoholism and drug abuse and suicide
are far worse in indigenous communities
than they are in any other
african-american whatever disadvantaged
group and we were embarked in this
journey of figuring stuff out we have
this horrible ecological problems human
beings are just trying to plan it we can
do water harvesting and we can do this
and we can do passive solar and thinking
that so much of it had to do with
technology and I was supposed to be up
in the front of the room and this old
man gets up and I'm thinking what are
you doing I'm this is important and he
looked around to everybody there was
after lunch and everybody's a little
sleepy and chatty and he said everybody
make a hit make a fist and hold it up he
holds up his fist and he says see how
your knuckles go up and down up and down
up and down just like the mountain ridge
just like the water in the valley look
at a spiral on your hand just like the
water in the drain or behind the rock or
the trout sits like a big storm and then
he looked at every one of
pointed his finger everyone of us and he
said no square people here we all belong
and he was governor of the pueblos mr.
Kinsella and he did this marvelous thing
where we were telling this story that
human beings are bad and we got to
figure out how to be better and we have
to use our intelligence to design
systems that are less bad and maybe they
could help heal things Hey but basically
human beings are bad and he said no we
are here for a reason right and our job
is to figure out that reason right and
he would say remember our original
instructions right and to to discover
what each of us is alive to give back to
the rest of the community human and
other than human more than human however
you want to talk about it that's a
they're all we're all people right
there's the rock people in the tree
people under right and so there's
something very Buddhist in there and it
makes me realize that I'm we're
constantly making these dichotomies good
bad that because we have this mechanical
mindset we're always trying to identify
the bad part that is to blame for the
problem and repair remove or replace it
we do this in foreign policy there's the
bad guy take him out
there's the guy dealing drugs take him
out there's the spark plug right it's
what we do and if we do it in an
environmental movement petrochemicals we
gotta get rid of oh this bank is funny
we got to get rid of instead of that
kind if we're all here for a reason and
that the whole question is which is a
harder question how do we regenerate us
all how do we make petrochemicals a
force for regeneration how do we make
the banking industry of force for
regeneration how do we shift our our
minds our hearts our beings our
worldviews our whole our souls so that
we take on this responsibility and
opportunity of being human beings to
play this co-creative regenerative role
within the living world and that to me
is far more inspiring then you're bad
and you're destroying the plan you're
going to kill everything and stop it
right and that I the beginning of my
book these days is what if climate
change is the best thing that's ever
happened to us what if it is the thing
that is enough to get us to wake up and
pay attention
and rise to what we're all capable of
right the the beauty and miraculousness
human beings are capable of is is
amazing right in architecture and art
music and kindness and creativity's of
all sorts and so that you know it's
funny this I was telling the story of
how I got here and within being part of
ree-ree Genesis I had a student I was
teaching permaculture and it was this
Community College course they had a
different teacher every week and I came
in and this young guy kind of latched on
to me started to travel around with me
solar laws his name and he wanted to
learn by going with me teaching and so
he started to contribute things so he
began to use the Thanksgiving address in
the morning and do some workout things
and he taught me how to make fire and
pretty soon I met his teacher John
Stokes who started something called the
tracking project yeah we're good
asking more about that so please
continue so I began to work with John
and learn from him he and I we went out
to Navajo land to do something and so
we're in the car 8 hours together and we
got out and he said oh you've read the
other half of the same library I've been
reading the
point being that with the library of
life rain of living systems and that I
was looking for larger systems point of
view and here's looking at tracks writ
large right so I've learned a lot from
working there and it's I need to be out
right I can't just be in my head or
talking to people and it also is connect
right tracking his storytelling right
you're reading the tracks in the ground
in the landscape just like reading a
book right so a few years ago we were in
this place in the mountains of New
Mexico where we go often and I looked
around and I realized ah there's not a
tree
except maybe these oak trees right by
the ranch house that's over 100 years
old that 100 years ago this was
clear-cut there was nothing here and
though today it's a forest it was not in
right this is something that we often I
got noticed this here on my oka that
people have an idea of what the original
landscape looks like and then if you
just scratch the surface a bit and look
at the into the history we came for
example everybody thinks of Mayorkas
the land of the almond blossom and
almond trees around the landscape and
really it was in the 1930s when the the
vine rock came in the destroyed the vine
and why grapes industry in both France
and also came to me oka that all the the
vineyards were ripped up and the almonds
came into it it's not that old right
yeah and so how do we use what we see so
that in our minds eye we can see this
longer story this process and every
story has a trajectory and our lives are
in one little piece of this millennial
you know multi-million year story and
how can we play a role in that so it's
moving in one direction or the other
and the thing that is striking to me is
all these things permaculture and the
living systems thinking through
Regenesis that comes down to the Sufis
in kerchief and Charlie Crone and
tracking they're all pattern ways of
looking at the world you're you're
looking at the surface to see what's
essential what is out of time and space
that's behind it because it's there that
we can work that makes the mechanical
world a physical world different whereas
if we don't change that we can make the
physical world different but it will
revert because that's that's that's the
fascinating thing about that idea of
resilience that so many people think
resilience is always necessarily a good
thing but but really the resilience of
the degenerative patterns that we've
created and we were talking earlier the
the the way our minds have been calling
not colonized with certain thought forms
and organizing ideas
that's what bounces back we try to keep
great things and we think yes we've
achieved something look at this that's
an example we can do it everywhere now
copy paste and then we're surprised it
doesn't work because the the system is
built around resilient patterns that
perpetuated in its degenerative patterns
if we don't go to the level of patterns
and bright but briefly and just for the
sake of people learning more about it
because I when I looked at your website
and I can I kicked through to the
tracking project I was struck by a
hundred thousand people having gone
through that program and having worked
with kind of vision fast and in solo
time in nature and time outside myself
and while I haven't done any of the
tracking work like the John Young eight
shields path and myself yet also deeply
resonating with that approach in seeing
how transformative it is to people so
learning about yet another watering hole
an organization that has taken a hundred
thousand people through such a program
please share bit wonders they happen
life program that I think you're also
important yeah I want to say one thing
before we get there okay so this you
were talking about the colonized mind
right so Paulo Freire is in pedagogy
impress coined that term and he was
looking at why is it that we have these
remarkable revolts and then the
previously oppressed people when they
get into power they're as bad as the
people that were in power before them
and I was in Zimbabwe a few years ago
teaching permaculture and I got to see
this firsthand and when I was in college
Zimbabwe was a great hope for all of us
right there's Bob Marley songs about it
Bob went there and and it's as you're
saying because if our minds still think
that power is overpowering when we get
into power that's what we will do right
and so I think mostly what we're up
against is is how do we not decolonize
our minds but rehumanize our mind sorry
indigenous our minds that we are part of
a living system and we begin to think
and work in that way and it's striking
to me right even resilience is a
physical mechanical term it's not even a
biological term even like what's the
biological mechanism for that what would
be and so I'm always trying to notice
how my mind is colonized by that
mechanical point of view and how I might
think about it and phrase it differently
how we would you it's difficult with the
language languages we've got so one of
the things so the TRACON project my
friend John Stokes he was in Australia
many years ago and follow young woman
there and he ended up teaching at an
Aboriginal community college and all
these old guys began to teach him things
and he wasn't trying to learn any of
this stuff and they taught him to play
didgeridoo and they taught him to track
by like
taking him to the park and watching kids
get off the bus and say oh that one
doesn't have a dad at home you know that
mom what you can't kick the soccer ball
nobody showed him how and so he realized
they were constantly tracking they and
then he came back to this country
someone set him to meet Tom Brown and he
said oh that's a word I can use for all
this stuff I'm learning that I would
like the urban Aboriginal guys to learn
and appreciate from their culture so he
went and found this guy Jimmy James
uncle Jimmy who was in the same town and
a famous tracker and hung out with Jimmy
for a few years and then came back and
taught at the track in school in New
Jersey and then came with a handful of
guys out here and to New Mexico and when
he had been going back and forth they
had used him as a runner so at that time
they were seeing aquas hustling notes
from Hosanna shown a the Iroquois
country about land right so they said go
meet those guys for us and tell us take
them this message and tell us what they
said and so when he got back to the
states and they asked him to help train
their young people and so he formed a
tracking project to help fund that so
and that has since spread worldwide and
it's kind of we joke all the time that
the tracking project is like a few
coolers and a bag of fire sticks and a
bag of Arnie sticks and a few tents and
sleeping bags that there's it's not in
the stuff right and it's all on the
remarkable people that have come through
the project and contributed to it and
acted as teachers and mentors and and so
I've learned a lot from that way of
looking at things and John's way of
working and he too is a wonderful
storyteller
and has taught me a lot about how do we
actually communicate and how do we
actually work on shifting fields so
he tells the story of these people came
to a tracking class to learn about I
said John here's how we got on our
notebooks and he they were blank and
they said we don't know what you did to
create leadership and community but you
did it in everything you did so that's
that tracking piece that's that pattern
piece it's not what you do it's how you
do it how do you teach fire-making in a
way that causes internal locus of
control how do you teach tracking so
that it gets people to consider it
externally to be able to see
systemically in a living biological
world how do you run things so that
everybody feels like they have a
leadership role whether they're four or
forty right so and that's also behind
all the work we're doing every Genesis
it's not about what we're doing it's how
we're doing it
right and how are we getting it the
biggest thing the two things I'm
realizing more and more Danielle that
are so important the first one is
getting to that place where I don't know
and asking for help
whatever that means internally and
externally because otherwise I'm just
doing the same old crap I've done before
it's things I've thought before and the
other one is to set the bar high for
everyone and everything that everyone
here is as capable as I am that they are
excuse me it's about me helping them be
creative it's not about me being the
creative genius which is again I mean
all of this is so deeply resonant with
indigenous wisdom from First Nations
people all over the globe the little
glimpses I'm nowhere near got the same
depth of having and privileged enough to
learn from people directly like you have
for so many years but like for example
working with Gigi Coyle and people from
the school of
borders and doing a Vision Quest there
and sitting in council and there have
been moments where I've touched into
that world or like talking with Dominic
and and with Jason about their
experiences in Australia it's it's so
fundamental to keep an apprentice
program mind not the hero mindset of of
our storytelling of it like even I think
this this this hero's journey story that
people get so into is still far too
focused on this idea that it's one
individual that is gonna take people to
safety and and really yeah how do we
enable everyone to bring forth a healthy
whole in which everyone can keep
evolving learning and and in this dance
with humility this paradox that we're
now faced with such urgency because of
the mess that we made with so much of
the biosphere and we have runaway
climate change and and cascading
ecosystems collapse and and again like
the back coming back to the question
that you start your book with which I
also want to talk about and like this
could the guy I often leaning towards
what I've learned in rite-of-passage
work and and working with council and
the wheel of the four directions
maybe climate change is that point in
which humanity at the species level is
put through a rite of passage which has
this will happen that I think lies at
the heart of why you called Regenesis
Regenesis that we actually need to face
our face our own death and die to the
patterns that no longer serve in order
to stay current and serve the greater
whole it's this Jana base is beautiful
and hospice workers and midwives it's
that
role of constantly embracing collapse
and and patterns dissolving if they're
not the right patterns any longer and
constantly listening with humility of
what wants to be born and that I think
we need to come back to and like you
earlier said the word rien digitization
which is for me something that that that
I more and more ask myself how do I do
this where I am with my family as the
way of sourcing and resourcing my work
to really live that how do I become
indigenous to ghost island and that that
I've chosen to to live on but yeah they
tell me a little bit more about em as
far as I understand as a synthesis of
your personal framing you have come to
call all these drunk from it and
integrate it in your work you call it
pattern mind and and now you finally
putting it into a book and I say finally
because it would be a gift for all of us
to be able to to read that and can you
say a bit more about this what you
understand uniquely about Pat and mine
and and and also please talk about your
forthcoming book of it yeah I would love
to and I want to say one thing about
this idea of indigenous peoples rien
digitizing that there is it's easy for
us all to romanticize native peoples and
that it's one of the things that I
learned living on the reservation for
almost 10 years as there's it's been bad
it's been horrific right and we're lucky
that
people have held on to what they've held
on to and that this is true of all of us
right that the Indian schools the Native
American schools and the aboriginal
schools in Australia off those that were
purposely to D culture and to colonize
people and their minds were just the
latest iteration of this process that's
gone on for a long time anything took it
was only a few years ago I realized when
I was a kid top taught was taught about
indentured servants and these were
people that came over to colonize
America and they would get passage over
for free and they only had to go work
for peoples for seven years
well if your lifespan is thirty years
seven years as a chunk that and like
peasants and serfs and we were slaves
our ancestors were slaves right all
around the world this was the case and
that was where colonization began right
and it's why then we went on and became
colonizing armies because we were
convinced at that that right and so this
it's why I used the word rien digitising
with that in mind that we have this
shared history of colonization of
abusive of all of those things I want
every side of it and in the tracking
project came upon Paulo Freire II in the
colonized mind and then also there's
this whole story from the hold initially
of the formation of the Confederacy the
Iroquois Confederacy of the story the
great peacemaker and a big piece of that
his message is about peace the good mind
and power that true power is from peace
and you must have a good mind to realize
that that if you your mind is distorted
and troubled by trauma and things you've
done things have happened to you and all
you cannot see the value of peace it's
only when you because you want us I was
right to be angry and act out I was
right that that's what we all do and so
there's a great depth to that story that
can be read in a book called the white
roots of peace and a big chunk of it is
a a condolence healing a straightening a
standing back up of ourselves and within
the ecological design realm there's a
wonderful book called tending the wild
by MCAT Anderson it's about California
and the use of fire and other
disturbances by native people to
regenerate those landscapes and this
idea that human beings by getting their
food fiber shelter energy all their
needs met increased species diversity
increase the biological strength and
power of ecosystems an entirely
different story than the one we've been
telling the mechanical story of us not
belonging and that this is looking
likely true all around the world there's
just recently and I mean we've all heard
the stories of a few years back of
showing that the Amazon largely Terra
Preta soils being basically plant
gardens but but just a few weeks ago in
I think the central plains and some
discoveries were made where it's it's
clear that there were American cities
that were literally farming the prairies
and that the numbers of bison roaming
was was increased through careful
stewardship and and when even the the
chests that old forests of the
northeastern you know North America that
was because of burning and planting
there's all this work wonderful book
black EMU
from Australia of firestick farming and
how the waterways were worked with and
your
Kian examples and all around the world
human beings understood their places
well enough to know where when and how
to make tiny changes that helped to
regenerate the system to another level
just just recently I was talking to one
of the people that I'm learning from
here on my akka and real craftsmen and
permaculture has regenerative
agriculture stand and stonemason of Nia
valleys and he's writing a book about
the history the past and the future of
Agriculture at the moment and his
research he is just tunneling into
really everything he's sort of slightly
on the spectrum and the way he works
with stop it beautiful way and he he
told me the story that the Iberian
Peninsula was the first place the Roman
want to be Empire started to invade and
it was the last place they built the
entire empire until they actually
colonized the Iberian and you know why
it was a clash of two agricultural
systems it was an acorn people against
the wheat people and they were trying to
bring in the wheat culture into an econ
culture and when he told me that I
thought that that's the story in North
America and that's what Mollison used to
say it's it's the Battle of humanity
between three people and grass people
and it's grass grains or or pastoralism
and you may know right Andalusia was an
oak forest and that the Oaks were cut to
smelt the silver that was mine in Spain
that funded the late Roman Empire so
there's great vast plains and done kilt
it's what you're talking about
my Orca right we think that what we know
is what has been so you in the
systems-thinking work that the living
systems thinking work we are engaged
with through Regenesis there's this idea
of disruption or disturbance our typical
thought patterns right because we're
such
creatures of habit like every other
living being that we will stay in that
rut until something kicks us out right
and what seems like a nice groove
eventually becomes an inescapable rut
and so I began thinking about ah well in
martial arts shoot and it's even in
permaculture right the least change for
the greatest effect right and the
problem is the solution yeah
oh well that's firestick farming right
and it's also what you're doing to
people's consciousness and so I thought
cool I got that so permaculture I
decided was not about designing things
but it was about observing the
trajectory of ecosystem ecological
succession what level are we at what
would be the little disturbance that
least changed for the greatest effect
that would bump the system up to another
level of ecological succession right
which is what we see native peoples
doing all around the world it's usually
taking what we call a climax system
that's senescent and some disturbance
moves it back to sub climax so
everywhere we look sub climatic systems
are more species diverse and more
productive Aspen are far more productive
than the spruce fir the chestnut oak far
more productive and each maple you know
everywhere you look that's the case as
well as there's cascading impacts from
that you you burn a mosaic pattern in
the forest and kills the thin bark trees
and encourages the nut trees but it also
buffers the pH of the soil it's also
been a buffer the pH of the waters as
well as the pH in the estuaries what's
going to enable all those shellfish to
bloom so you have oysters sufficient in
the Chesapeake Bay to filter all the
water within 24-48 hours but then I
began to realize oh wait a second it's
not just about disruption like we keep
talking about so commonly in this era
right it's not just you disrupt
something and something new will emerge
something may emerge but it may not be
better right or it may not be richer so
you have to do the tracking you have to
do the observation you have
notnot be a part of the system and
observe in this a non-attached way right
so that's like if if the disturbance is
where the seed is on the the soil
surface there's all the root work that
needs to go into deciding what that
disturb what story I'm going to tell you
right because most of us heard a story
had an experience read a book had a
teacher that totally altered the
direction of our lives and then there's
the whole branching of the tree we must
practice it we must continue with other
people to be engaged in this process of
reusing ourselves of developing
ourselves our minds right our whole
minds as nested within larger beings
that were part of that our minds right
we it's my burger Bateson's whole point
is that an ecosystem and a species all
of us bear the marks of mind I think as
we were edging I mean these both these
topics of where does life begin and
where does it end you like like I was
singing these guy in cycles like the
carbon in my lung now it's here was it
like remnant and now it's dead and the
similar way I think we like at the if we
really go upstream it is reframing how
we think about what is life and and
understand this life as a planetary
process that manifests through us but
that all the wisdom traditions speaking
about eternal life speak about the Gaian
cycles of eternal when you sink in with
them then you're given eternal life
because like then you're thinking of
yourself as an expression of 3.8 billion
years of evolutionary journey but
similarly mind even beyond that if we
have this function I'm it's about
knowing yeah that consciousness is
primary that what we're seeing as
physical world is the in mattering of
consciousness and patterns of
consciousness which are patterns of
relationships and interactions and
information flow between momentary
jewels in the jeweled net of Indra
manifesting as you or me
or tree or and you don't have to answer
to this tangent but that's basically I
believe that this is this dynamic
phenomenological worldview where we
really bring forth the world in
conversation like Madonna and Marilla
might like to say and we everything
matters like our our conversation has
called agency across the fractal
patterns of place and and consciousness
yeah so for me the word that hits the
ground is in the tracking right which is
also the same ways people have navigated
the landscape every landscape right
you're talking about levels of landscape
there's a consciousness landscape
there's spiritual landscape there's a
physical landscape there's an ecological
landscape there's a socio-economic
landscape and the power of patterns is
that they apply across scale in media
right so that spiral on my hand applies
all the way up to galaxies a bright
waves cycles right the way nature makes
resources functionally infinite is by
cycling them I mean there doesn't have
to be infinite water just has to go up
and come down and go up and right and
trickle through the landscape and be
held in the landscape does it need to be
infinite money it just needs to cycle
round and that's also how
life is eternal its cycles of life right
before your daughter was born those
cells that made her were alive right
that goes all the way all the way back
and so for me it grounds always in place
and that includes me Who am I how do I
work what are the gifts I have to give
and even beyond that you know David Bohm
he says when we talk about subatomic
particles we're going to a mechanical
mind set those particles are fields
they're waves right and so one of the
things we're always working on is how do
we shift the field and as long as we're
telling a story which is we are bad and
the only way to work is by shifting
things mechanically and by guide we're
gonna stop this bad things and we're
good right well and do the good things
yeah that's where you see very directly
consciousness making the world right
because of the way I see the world
I do certain things that makes cups and
laws and all kinds of stuff right but if
I go to of the most effective place to
work where causality works is in
shifting the underlying patterns and
feels and that's something we need to do
together I can't go off and do that for
anybody right there's this the I was
thinking about some I don't know if
you've read the hero with a thousand
masks yes Joseph Campbell in the
introduction he talks about regeneration
and this is right at the end of World
War two and he's saying war is a trap
peace is a trap failure is a trap
success is a trap that we turn anything
into a rut we increasingly solidify that
structure instead of realizing that no
just like the structure of my body that
structure serves at a certain
point but it must restructure and
restructure and restructure and
restructure and those patterns are what
continues throughout so that if and
that's what pattern mind is all about is
how do we shift to seeing a living world
of patterns and be alive in that world
of patterns instead of in a world of
physical structural things and then how
do we read that landscape to see aa
little nudge here a little shift in this
underlying pattern we don't have the
time and energy empowered to regenerate
to rebuild restore the living systems of
the planet but we do have the capability
to do is shift the underlying patterns
that would enable it to regenerate
itself and it's one of these reasons we
use the term this is because
regenerative design I don't think really
exists because I can regenerate myself I
can serve to the regeneration of my
community but I can't regenerate you or
your community it has to cut
regeneration must be from within so what
we're always working on is building that
capacity and that capability and that's
why if I'm the expert supplying the
answer it doesn't develop anybody's
capability or capacity it's working with
people and place us in a way so they
developed the answer they developed the
path yeah I mean that's that's so
resonant with I mean that's why like I a
purposefully put designing regenerative
culture has a paradox in it and its
culture emerges in isn't is never
designed but we are co-created through
our four patterns what we communicate
and how we communicate even just what we
pay attention to and and how we pay
attention that's why like I've got 250
questions running through my book in
order to invite that practice of not at
the end of us chapter saying ah I've
just talked about by regional
development here the ten principles of
bio regional development
the minute you just reformulate those 10
principles into 10 questions that still
speak to the patterns behind principle
you invite people's participation and
you understand that co-creating
regenerative cultures is about living
the questions together but tell me a
little bit more about the book you're
writing right now because so it's it's
bringing these three threads together
because there's they're all thresholds
to see me pattern world living systems
thinking the permaculture ecological
design and the tracking right well sure
you could just as easily call navigation
how do we see the patterns of the world
to guide us yeah and using those and
particularly stories to help people see
things anew I mean so even that story of
mr. Quinn chela that oh no Square people
here right it totally changed the way I
was seeing the world and maybe just for
a minute right so then I have to
practice in some way to continually
ricci the world to continually question
the things I'm most certain of and
that's hard work and something we can't
do alone right and it's something that
must be practiced so this is all meant
to be there's this image amongst the
ocean they have the white roots of
pieces that's why the name of the book
about that story is that and someone
were to encounter the little white root
tips of the tree of peace they could
follow those roots back to the tree of
peace and take shelter there and learn
about peace and so it's one of the ways
I'm seeing this book is there are many
things included in it from all the
teachers I've had throughout my life
even if I just encountered them in books
or they were trees or mountains or
whatever so that people could follow
those little roots back to those sources
and
it's told as a large arc through little
stories and lifting the patterns out and
helping us Ricci the way we see the way
we see ourselves in the way we see life
so that we can engage pattern level and
actually work in the way that we must be
working if we want to regenerate the
planet not just a rest death which is as
you're saying that's the wrong way of
thinking about it but what is the core
pattern of how nature does work right
you mentioned before we began to record
this Gregory Bateson's quote about most
of our problems come from thinking
differently than nature work so how does
nature work how does life work how would
we actually look at ourselves see how do
we really work despite what our brains
habits tell us is how we work and it is
through this pattern of regeneration
which is about not creating a dichotomy
but seeing what is the potential and
what appears to be an economy what is
the value behind what we love and what
we hate and this very Buddhist approach
of what is and what does that enable
what is the potential of the future so
that permaculture principle of the
problem is the solution then if we take
that seriously what would it mean that
climate change is the solution
petrochemicals is the solution globalism
colonialism all of those things that's
where we should be looking for
regeneration that's the source of
regeneration it's in the shadow it's in
the muck it's in the dirt it's in the
what we were trying to cut off right
absolutely I think this is this for me
that this was a gift because I've been I
moved to Majorca almost eight years ago
now with this intention like after
having spent a lot of time at eco
villages and and working with transition
towns looking at the community scale of
whole systems design for sustainability
and all that
and I realized that the real
transformative patterns have to be and
looking at that that nested wholeness
goodbye regional-scale I think so yes
it's in place but we have to scale
inking that design and that somehow in
the the synergies you can build between
communities and places within a
watershed or within an island like
Majorca is where where things can really
well even that conversation where you
engage people at the regional scale to
say what is the potential of this place
can really flourish and and so for the
last eight years I've been sort of
acupuncture exploring wait how can I
start this conversation here and I've
worked with a couple of documentary
filmmakers that were making
documentaries about sort of stories of
hope and but recently I've basically
come to the conclusion that really has
just been affirmed with what you said
that since the island is 85% dependent
on tourism the only way to engage a
conversation powerful enough to shift
the patterns of their system is to turn
tourism the problem into the pathway for
regeneration and the key is we have no
idea how to do that exactly
that's it that's how to stop the
conversation and who involve in the
conversation and see what happens and
the thing that I've been learning over
the past few years particularly through
TRP the regenerative practitioner which
is this education program that you went
through through Regenesis is I've been
stuck on that greater whole being
something on the map that it is a
greater living hole and that living home
might be agriculture in the
Mediterranean hmm it might be the
economic system or if one of the living
wholes we're working with now is Natural
History Museum's as a living system
right and it made me realize again how
physical my mind is oriented even when
I'm thinking I'm thinking in living
systems terms that and I learned this
from my students working on some
projects with them in their coaching
cohorts and their resourcing cohorts
that I was going always to the watershed
watershed watershed and I had to realize
oh no we might be working on
architecture in a region we might be
working on forest regeneration in a
region and so I'm always learning how
colonized my mind is by a physical
mechanical Newtonian reality of the
world instead of this biological no even
the label of by region could could
become the fault trap like that
absolutely let me ask you something
because this is something that also
grapple with because I I noticed the
wonderful attention to language that
that is part of the Regenesis way of
working and and again there's always a
shadow side to that like a pet sometimes
can be a little bit more difficult but
that's an invitation to for deeper
learning at least be full of said I
didn't mind if people didn't understand
me but I didn't want to be misunderstood
and and but but even thinking of it as
patterns like if you use the framework
of spiral dynamics in the kind of the
integral human development patterns
where people are at different worldview
systems and ways of looking at the world
then M to what extent would you say that
minute you use patterns that are like
language forms and words concepts there
are still part of the mechanistic world
you you can't but perpetuate them or is
there skillful means way of saying well
in this context with these people the
only way I can begin the conversation is
using language that doesn't alienate
them and and brings them into the
conversation once they're rallying
around it like even like playing with
the fact that now people want to look at
the problem of climate change and they
might even be able to stretch to say
that the problem of climate change is a
symptom of a larger process and that
ecosystems collapse cuz getting
ecosystems by the biodiversity loss that
these are also all symptoms and the
fragility of our current economic system
is actually more upstream from that
because it's the economic system that
the problem and that's an expression of
the mindset and then you and then you
begin to to engage how do you work with
that like sometimes do you sometimes
kind of go here I go again using this
mechanistic language of these
mechanistic patterns in order to make
people hear in me and then I take them
on a deeper journey later or do you just
never do that it's a great question and
I'm not gonna
directly I've spent a lot of my life
being a bridge or a bit of a translator
between cultures
my mom was white anglo-saxon Protestant
my dad was Jewish of Ashkenazi descent
and in the 50s when they married that
was a big cultural difference so I grew
up in what may not now seem like a big
difference but I spent my childhood
translating for myself living between
two worlds and so a lot of the work I've
done around the world is communicating
to very different communities and
cultures and one of the things I've
learned from Carl Sandford which i think
is great you never meet people where
they are you lead them you see where
they are and you lead them so that's one
answer to what you're saying and also I
notice when I'm doing what you're doing
is it's again a mechanical point of view
here's the system here's where people
are I want to move them over here I'm
gonna use the words they can hear and
then I'll move them here and then I'll
move them there and that right and it's
the thing I always try to remind myself
of is that what really matters is what's
outside of time and space and what keeps
us trapped is that we are thinking we
are trapped in time and space and that
is what is core to a linear dichotomous
mechanical physical worldview right and
I don't always know how to do that and I
got to get to work on time the kids got
to get there and I could write but it's
what I have learned over the years
whether it's from sacred teachers or my
experience in the wilderness or working
with communities that the most effective
place to work is in the field shifting
the field that creates a different
physical reality that enables us to have
different thoughts to see different
things to be in different relationships
to one another and so I'm always looking
at how am i reverting to a mechanical
way of creating this living world
instead of going
know what is how would I be working on a
field mm-hmm Wow I mean this thank you
and I'm not always good at it I'm not
always successful good line I know that
that's that's where we've got a that's
what it would mean to really have a
pattern mind is that that's where we are
living because we're sort of at the end
of the conversation and for time reasons
but then two things I wanted to pick up
on um and now I've briefly have a
momentary lapse of you're out of time
and space yeah that's deep for me like
really because I I completely that was
what is another one of my hunches that
it's all about how we understand time in
space that is keeping us trapped but but
the way you just framed it and made me
see my own patterns beautifully it says
I think thank you for that um this was a
beautiful thing but the one thing before
I really don't want to let you off the
hook because I know that how to speak to
that but you also as you're writing this
book you're asking people for some
support so you can free the time to
really work on it a crowdfunding request
to help you work on it just breathe how
people where where to find that and and
what you're asking yes well it's as much
to help fund all the help
I'm meeting in editors and all of those
various and ciliary aspects as it is to
get me enable need to set some time
aside to get this done so I've been
working on this almost ten years and it
has morphed in many ways and changed the
many ways that I've gotten clearer and
clearer about what it needs to be and
I'm asking for help and my aim is for
$20,000 and I'm well on my way I've had
some very generous donors some
individuals and some groups that have
donated $2,000 and things like that and
I do not have to link up on my website
you're making me realize that I should
put that up on the website Daniel so
thank you for that it is on my Facebook
page which is Joel glands burg and it is
through the Institute for regenerative
practice the Regenesis Institute for
regenerative prep practice and you have
that link and if you would put that with
this video I would much appreciate it
and now I also know what-what dropped
earlier briefly wait to close and it
actually relates to this project of the
book and Eddie earlier when you were
speaking on ie I thought of this framing
of making tacit knowledge explicit and
suddenly I realized that is part of the
gift that the elders in Regenesis have
really been working on and it's
unfolding is how because it's one thing
to go on that journey of working of
tracking patterns of reading the
patterns of life of translating between
cultures of working with process to
shift process and learn that as a tacit
knowledge that you somehow kind of feel
what to say in the right moment or who
needs to talk to each other or M want
needs to happen next but it's it another
whole level to make that tacit
experience that you've built up through
all the stories all the learning all the
elders that you've been gifted by and
and to make that learning explicit and
and share it with others and I think
that's that's part of having only begun
the journey of learning from from this
amazing community that the Regenesis is
kind of in birth by and I think that's
that's one of the gifts that you're all
working on sharing your experience over
the last 3040 years of doing this work
but also as you have done this in this
conversation humbly with a kind of what
do we know right well it's it's why
we've talked we talked about this as a
school right is that this all came down
to us we didn't invent any of this
really it's just how do we apply it how
do we learn it how do we develop
ourselves and that it's why we started
the educational programs the development
programs community programs is because
if it dies with us that's no good right
it's like a martial arts or any kind of
lineage is that the teachers job the
sensei's job which means the person just
a little further down the path is to
make sure their students exceed beyond
excel beyond their abilities right
because if it's not going up each time
it's going down right and that's even
what I've tried to do in the
permaculture community is because it's
going to all turn into rhetoric and
Dogma unless we continually regenerate
it and question what we think we know
right so it's why the program you
intended the regenerative practitioner
began was because we were never going to
be able to grow Regenesis internally we
were going to have to help to develop a
community around the world that would do
their own work and we would mentor them
in their development so that they could
do this better and better in depth
because it's not a one-shot deal you
take a week-long course or a month-long
course and you've got the information it
really is beginning to understand how to
develop your capabilities so that's what
like just from me tracking the beginning
effects like and
hosted really stands out is Oakland a
and and the work in New Zealand but also
in Australia and and and the Bay Area
has a strong cohort now of multiple
graduates from the TRP coming together
and building and also the European edges
is growing after like we first European
TRP was here on New York and 2017 but
now there's one coming up and starting
today not tomorrow yes in which will end
in Portugal and they even talking about
doing another one because there's so
many people asking for it so I yes I
think that it's there's there's a need
for this wisdom and so I really I'm so
looking forward to your book and I'm I'm
excited that you're writing it and put
that link in and I'll also have somebody
in mind we enabled me to write my book
and with a generous donation who I would
like to tell about you and I'd be
wonderful thank you I appreciate that
Daniel I just want to say one word
everything you were just speaking to is
because we've been building the field
around regenerative development so TRP
is not just meant to educate people it's
to develop a field and that's why we've
begun to do them in nodes and places
because we learned from the New Zealand
one that having everybody be in a place
was much more powerful and enabled more
work to happen afterwards and in between
and that's why we just launched this
ongoing developmental series for people
that's eight sessions a year for TRP
grats yeah so yeah so we tried to walk
our talk and try to not just work on
mechanically shifting things but how do
we develop a field and enable people
like yourself to develop a field right
it's why you sponsored that European
cohort was because you saw it as a way
of building the field that would enable
all the work you're working on to be
easier more effective yeah and
hoping that after this next European
cohort your life becomes increasingly
easy and abundant well same same
blessings to you and to hopefully
everyone that's what we're working for
that life becomes increasingly abundant
for it for everyone it's not always
going to be easy because I think
sometimes and it's the pain that cracks
the shell of our understanding it
absolutely is that I keep thinking this
thing you know we keep talking about
nature's cooperative and we should be
cooperative and it makes me realize that
we may know that that's the key to
saving the planet but it doesn't tell me
how it doesn't tell me how to get along
with people it doesn't tell me how to
use conflict in the development away it
doesn't right it just is like the
ecological stuff be nice exhorting
people to be nice is not going to get us
where we need to go it's about enabling
us all to do the development to work
that's necessary including truly loving
our enemies truly seeing them as our
brothers sisters that's a great place to
leave people with and thank you so much
for this conversation and Thank You
Danielle be well you think this was
really beautiful thank you thank you I
look forward to more